in this episode we're going to look at swipey
commands swipey commands is a new concept that
is introduced on the GrandMA 3. it wasn't
a thing on GrandMA 1 or GrandMA 2
but they introduced it now and when i saw
it for the first time i wasn't really sure
if it was this thing i was going to use because i
mean there's a lot of buttons on the desk and we
can put macros in the windows and stuff like that
so the reason why it being being there was kind of
weird to me but now i tried starting to use it
and i think it's really really really really cool
but what is swipi commands the way we used to
work is you go into the group window for instance
and then you say okay i have all my wipers i want
to activate them i can say add full and then i can
move them around if i want to store this somewhere
i can go up into my command section up here open
the window go down and locate the store button
i can close the command section and then i can
store position preset right here that's kind of
cool but the new thing is that now you can store
it directly here without having to open the
command section for the most common commands
so if we say this one we just saved this
one maybe if we try to delete it we can
press it and hold the mouse down or your finger
if you're working on a real console and then you
simply drag the mouse outside the preset box and
then this appears and this is the swipey
so if we say okay now we save the preset right
here but we want to delete it we don't want it
anyway we can simply while we're still holding
the mouse or the finger on the screen you can
simply hold your mouse on top of delete and let
go and it's gone so now if we want to program
positions for instance like we did before we can
say okay we find a nice position right here and
we can press an empty one and drag it outside and
say store now we start a preset and we didn't have
to open the command section this works for some
some different things but not for everything of
course but but for the most common commands copy
move delete stuff like that it works so basically
now we made our first position and now we can
start building our show here our palette as we
as we prepared for last time we set up our 3d
view last time and we can start programming some
fixture positions i hope you like these videos
and if you do please uh give the video a thumbs
up that will mean a lot to us and maybe even
subscribe to the channel to be notified when
we upload new videos so right now my vipers are in
the first position right now they're just pointing
straight out what we can do now as we did in the
last one we can take our align tool the align tool
will fan the fixtures one way or the other way
depending on which which one of these you choose
but if we want to fade them to center or from
center you can simply have the dash here like
we did last time and then you can dial dial the
pan here and it will fan from center and out
on the GrandMA 1 uh or sorry on the
GrandMA 2 the align function for this was
this one and the previous one i don't know
why they changed it but let's see if we can
make it work so we just clear again take all
the vibers turn them on put them on preset one
and then take the align function the first one
the dash and then just fan them out a little bit
then we can say okay this is our second position
we simply drag it outside the box and say store
there we go and we merge it in so we want to
make let's say we want to make four positions
we tilt it up and we have a maybe
into the audience position here
there we go maybe a little bit more
there we go we store this one and then we
can take it all the way up into the air
and we store this right here now we made four
presets with our vipers our positions right here
and we didn't have to go into the command section
one time what we can do is continue and say okay
we want to label these presets we do it again
we push it we drag it outside the box and we say
label and we can just say position
one we can say position two we can say
audience and we can say maybe roof there we go
now we just saved our four positions on stage so
let's uh continue and say okay what else can we
do about these uh pellets and and positions like
this we need we have our vipers up here we just
saved our four positions but when i push my auras
you can see they're kind of grayed out
and that's because there's no information
inside these pallets that is referring to
the auras so let's just do the same thing
and save our four positions similar to the
other ones we'll just take the first one
like this one and we drag it out
and we say store and we merge it
then we fan it out a little bit like the other
ones we store it into position number two
and we merge then we take it to the audience
like this and we merge it in here and then we
point it up into the roof like this into the
air and we store it into this one there you go
now we made our four positions for our
vipers and our auras and we didn't even leave
this window under normal circumstances you
would have to open this one and say store
and then close it and push a button or
you could write store in the command line
we'll get back to the command line in a
later tutorial because you can actually do
everything from here as well but
that's that's for a different tutorial
so while we're at it let's uh let's make some
colors let's take the vipers and let's just uh
no let's actually do something different let's
just take the first viper and that's called 701
i push that one and only this fixture appears
let's go uh play with the colors a little bit
we don't have any colors lined up right now we
have the colors down here and of course we can
if we turn it on like this we can mix some colors
and and start playing around with it but of course
there's an easier way to do that we want to make
our color presets up here in this color pool up
here but we need to make a view with our color
picker first so what we can do now is delete our
screen we have our view stored up here like we
did in one of the first episodes of the tutorial
if we push that one up here remember we could
delete this screen over here if we push that
button under the display tab it's black and then
we push the button up here i just pushed any area
in inside the the the black part of the screen
and we under the common select our color picker
and that opens up a color picker you have four
different ways of doing it you have the swatch
book where you can go in and say okay i want a lee
color and if you are old like me you will remember
181 is congo blue and you'll
remember 106 being red and so on but
that's basically not the way we do it
anymore that's from the good old par cans
we can use our faders we can say okay i want a
full cyan no magenta and no yellow that'll just
give us a cyan or we can take the color picker
right here and say okay where do we want to be
for my sake i always want to start with having
an open white color on my color preset so i can
always get rid of the any color that's that's in
the preset so let's just drag it down to white
go back to my first view and then we can just
store this one up here now we made our first
color preset and we forgot to store
the view so let's just do this again
delete the screen and open the color
picker and we're back and then we can
i wonder if the swipeys are working up here
they're actually they're not i hope they will
someday so we go back into this one store this
one right up here and we just call it color
there we go so now we can switch between those
two views right here we start the white one up
here we can go back into the color tab select the
color picker right here and say okay the next one
is cyan maybe you see it turned cyan color
right here we can use our swipey to store the
cyan we can go into the maybe a magenta and
we go back and we store them at magenta color
and you see it always opens
on the wrong tab right here
and that's a that's one of the things about views
wherever you leave it it's going to come back to
when you so if you store it like this every time
you push it it's going to be like this so if we
push this one and say okay this is what i want
to see all the time then you can say store
and on top of the color we say okay and now when
i go back to the view we have our color picker
so right now we start our cyan we start
our magenta let's just store a yellow
maybe red color
and let's just uh let's just find the
blue color and then let's call it a day
all right now we stored white cyan magenta yellow
red and blue i like to i like to label them and
we can use the swiping command to do that as
well you drag it outside the box you label it
we label it white
we label this one cyan
we label it magenta
and we take yellow here
red and finally the blue color but remember we
only stored one light inside these pallets we only
took the first uh moving light right here but we
have 11 others of this type and we have 12 other
auras up here so what are we going to do if
we clear this out and we select the vipers
and we turn them on at full and we go into
cyan notice that they are all cyan right
now and that's because we just stored a
global preset up here a global preset is
a reference to the color wheels you have on your
fixtures you have a cyan magenta yellow or you
have a rgb or you have amber or blue depending on
what kind of fixture it is and the desk recognize
that if the fixture has the same parameters you
can make a global preset and then it work on
all the moving lights so if we clear this out
and we take the auras and we turn them at full
sorry we need to clear out the vipers
there we go and then we take the rs
at full and we try it again up here now it
doesn't work because it's not the same fixture
so now we save the color information for all the
vipers like this let's clear out and let's take
the auras and see okay now it it's grayed out
again so we need to do the same thing again
for all the auras but we can just merge it in
on top of the other one so let's just say it
full go into the color picker pick cyan and so on
and do all the other colors as well i'm going to
speed up the video right here so you can you
don't have to watch me do it all over again
so now we stored all our vipers and all our auras
on top of this on these ones they're still global
now so now they contain the information from all
the vipers and all the auras you have to be a
little bit careful with using the color picker if
you use the color picker it will it will be more
creative for you because you can you can find
the exact blue color you want but the danger is
that you're going to lose some light because
if you want to do a proper blue and only want
to turn on the blue leds in the moving light you
would want the cyan and magenta to be at full both
of them if you have a little bit of yellow inside
or a little bit less cyan as we did right before
you lose a little bit of light but then
it's up to you how creative you want to be
but if you want full power make sure just to
turn on the blue led like you can see over here
when you use the the rgb color mixer over here
this is full blue and if you see right here it
adds some red to it so that's the danger of
using the color picker but it doesn't matter
which one you use as long as you're happy
and as long as you you like the way it looks
let's clear this and then say okay what do we
need to do now let's just do a little bit of
global information and last time i saved my gobo
information up here but i'd rather have it down
here actually so let's just close the focus window
move the gobo down here and then drag it all the
way out and then add the focus information up here
so let's say we have all the vipers we turn them
at full and we say okay the focus information it's
this one down here let's see what options we have
we have some zoom information let's just
zoom them all the way in and we store this
i'd like to have the the standard
here so this would be my normal 50
then we could do a narrow here and we can
do a wide here but that's up to you how you
how you want to work so we store this
one then we zoom it all the way out
there we go and we store this one here and
then we see if we can find the the default
and we store this one right here so now let's
just label this we label it and we say standard
we say
narrow and when you label these ones you don't
have to you basically don't have to use the
the swipeys and push the label button you can
just press it and say wide on your keyboard
so that's the same thing depending on how you
want to work what we can also look at on the swipe
is some of the other other things here you can
assign stuff to different views that's also for a
later tutorial you can delete them like this it's
gone then we can just type oops down here we can
move it over here or we can copy it over
here let's just delete that one again
and let's just move this one
back into position right here
so that's pretty cool that's working with
swipey swipe is is brilliant and while we've
been working with swipes we actually started our
programming session for all this stuff up here and
this is going to be the basis for when we start
to program our show for real so let's just finish
it with the some global information down here and
say okay which of these moving lights contain gobo
information that would be the vipers we go into
gobo we take gobo number one gobo wheel number one
and we go into channel sets and there you'll
see the the five gobos and the the open gobo
you can just push it and select it and then we can
store it right here that would be the open gobo
and dots in space we store this right here and
you can see the gobo appears on the palette which
is pretty cool then we can say happy down here
and then we can say oh i don't like the limbo
one i like this one this one and we store
this one down here so now we have no gobo
gobo number one which we want to use the second
one we only use and the third one we're gonna use
depending on what kind of show you do i don't
know i i always store two maybe three gobos
and then then that's gonna be fine last but not
least we have the beam here and the beam option is
some strobe options some iris options some frost
and you can see right here it says beam one of
three so this is basically page one you have
your four encoder wheels that's number one
you pay press it right here and then it changes
to four other options and last but not least you
push it on to page number three and then you have
the last option so beware that in some cases stuff
will be hidden behind this one you can see rgb
here on the color tab if you push it you will
have some static colors you have some cto some
more color mixing some you can tweak the color
temperature if you're making a tv show but but
just be aware if there's something you can't find
most likely it'll be hidden between these ones and
somewhere right here on the right side of the left
side or i don't remember where they are there's a
suggestions for a playlist that will cover all the
episodes on our GrandMA 3 tutorial journey so
if you want to learn GrandMA 3 programming or if
you want to learn to use the GrandMA 3 lighting
desk of the lighting console from MA lighting
please check one of our other videos thanks for
watching and i hope to see you next time bye bye